Guide to the Pierrepont family papers ARC.263
Brooklyn Historical Society
Pierrepont family papers
1761-1918
Brooklyn Historical Society
Pierrepont family
Pierrepont, Henry Evelyn
Pierrepont Stores (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Pierrepont, John Jay
ARC.263
94.55 Linear Feet in 7 manuscript boxes and 85 flat boxes
The Pierrepont family papers (1761-1918) document the intersection of commercial, civic and personal interests across three generations of one of the most prominent and influential families of nineteenth century Brooklyn, New York. The bulk of the collection concerns the business dealings of Henry Evelyn Pierrepont from 1838 to his death in 1888. This especially includes an extensive set of accounting and transactional records concerning the Pierrepont Stores, the family's warehouse on Brooklyn's East River waterfront; these include records of ships arriving at the Stores and their cargoes delivered. Additionally, there are substantive correspondence, legal documents and other materials concerning the Union Ferry Company, of which Henry was an officer. In addition to commerce and shipping, a major theme of the collection is that of land acquisition in Brooklyn Heights and at the adjacent waterfront in the early nineteenth century, and the development of that property over the course of the century. Included in the collection are correspondence, deeds, indentures, leases, accounting records, diaries, maps, invoices, receipts, business proposals, legal filings, clippings, and historical and genealogical manuscripts.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection is comprised of several accessions. Explicit documentation of the provenance for most of these accessions is lacking. Evidence exists that most of the material included in the collection was donated by Pierrepont family members who were active participants in The Long Island Historical Society (re-named Brooklyn Historical Society in 1985) from its founding in 1863. The papers were received over a period of approximately seventy-five years, from the late nineteenth century through 1962. Copy of disputed will of H.B. Pierpont is the gift of Charlotte Beagle, 2015.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in the following series:
Series 1: Mercantile, Farm and Distillery
Series 2: Personal and Social Matters
Series 3: Brooklyn Real Estate
Series 4: Pierrepont Stores
Series 5: Rail Lines in Brooklyn
Series 6: Brooklyn Waterfront and Ferries
Series 7: Newspaper Clippings
Series 8: Diaries
Biographical note
Timeline
1768 Hezekiah Beers Pierpont born in New Haven, Connecticut
1790 H.B. Pierpont moved to New York City
1793 Mercantile partnership Leffingwell and Pierpont founded
1800 Leffingwell and Pierpont dissolved
1802 Marriage of H.B. Pierpont and Anna Maria Constable
1804 Pierponts moved to Brooklyn, New York
1808 Henry Evelyn Pierrepont born in Brooklyn, New York;H.B. Pierpont purchased Livingston brewery
1819 Anchor Gin Distillery closed
1836 H.E. Pierrepont purchased stock in a Brooklyn ferry lease
1838 Death of Hezekiah Beers Pierpont
1841 Marriage of H.E. Pierrepont and Anna Maria Jay
1844 H.E. Pierrepont and Jacob R. Leroy organized Union Ferry Company
1845 Henry Evelyn Pierrepont II born
1849 John Jay Pierrepont born
1856-57 Pierrepont Stores erected
1864 H.E. Pierrepont appointed President of Green-WoodCemetery
1869 Marriage of H.E. Pierrepont II and Ellen A. Low
1876 Marriage of John Jay Pierrepont and Elise de Rham
1879 H.E. Pierrepont authored Historical Sketch of the FultonFerry
1881 Fire at Pierrepont Stores (June)
1888 Death of H.E. Pierrepont. Pierrepont Stores leased to Empire Warehouse Company
1895 Pierrepont Stores sold to Brooklyn Wharf and Warehouse Company
1911 Death of Henry Evelyn Pierrepont II
1923 Death of John Jay Pierrepont
Hezekiah Beers Pierpont:
Hezekiah Beers Pierpont amassed a fortune through the operation of a farm and gin distillery, and through real estate investments in the Village and City of Brooklyn during the first three decades of the nineteenth century. Born in New Haven, Connecticut on November 3, 1768, Hezekiah settled in New York City in 1790 where he worked as a clerk in the Customs House. By 1793, Hezekiah had set out on his own ventures, forming the mercantile partnership Lefingwell and Pierpont. The partnership dissolved in 1800 and Hezekiah moved to Brooklyn in 1801 after purchasing the brewery of Philip Livingston and converting it to a distillery for what became Anchor Gin. The following year he married Anna Maria Constable, daughter of Anna White and William Constable of Philadelphia. The couple came to have twelve children together, including Henry Evelyn Pierrepont.
During this period, Pierpont became known for his support of the development of the Village of Brooklyn. He began to invest in local real estate in 1802, focusing his investments around present-day Brooklyn Heights, directly across the East River from lower Manhattan. Pierpont supported the Fulton Ferry, which began the first steam ferry service between Brooklyn and Manhattan in 1814, making Brooklyn even more accessible to New York City. At this same time, Pierpont acquired additional wealth through the inheritance and purchase of more than 150,000 acres of land in upstate New York from the estate of his father-in-law.
Hezekiah retired from active business in 1819 and closed the distillery, which was sold in 1824. He committed much of his time to the improvement of both residential and business sections of Brooklyn Heights, proposing such developments as a promenade to be situated along the bluffs overlooking the East River and New York Harbor. Hezekiah Beers Pierpont died in Brooklyn on August 11, 1838.
(Note on the Pierpont name: For a period of time the original spelling of the family name, Pierrepont, was superseded by the anglicized spelling Pierpont. Hezekiah Beers Pierpont requested that his wife and children be known by the original spelling of Pierrepont around 1802, but did not himself adopt this spelling for business reasons.)
Henry Evelyn Pierrepont:
The second son of Hezekiah Beers and Anna Maria Constable Pierrepont, Henry Evelyn was born in Brooklyn on August 8, 1808. Henry Evelyn was educated in New York City and quickly acquired his father's prominence among Brooklyn's elite. Upon the death of H.B. Pierpont, William Constable, the eldest Pierrepont son, took over the family's upstate properties while Henry Evelyn remained in Brooklyn, maintaining the family's influence on, and commitment to, the city's development. On December 1, 1841, Henry Evelyn married Anna Maria Jay, daughter of Peter Augustus Jay and Mary Rutherford Clarkson, and granddaughter of John Jay, governor of New York (1795-1801) and the first Chief Justice of the United States. Together the couple had six children, including Henry Evelyn Pierrepont II and John Jay Pierrepont.
Henry Evelyn Pierrepont spent much of his life working to establish Brooklyn as a flourishing metropolis. In 1844 a Brooklyn ferry lease was granted to Henry Evelyn Pierrepont and Jacob R. Leroy, who combined the five existing Brooklyn ferries into the Brooklyn Union Ferry Company. The venture created a more frequent and regular service between Brooklyn and New York City, and effectively monopolized transportation across the East River prior to the completion of the Brooklyn Bridge in 1883.
By 1857 Henry Evelyn and William Pierrepont had established a joint venture, the Pierrepont Stores, "a United States bonded warehouse where ships' freight was received and stored for the owners, insured by the government, until duties were paid." The Stores was a major port of entry for a number of different cargoes (primarily sugar and molasses) from locales ranging from the Caribbean to Manila. Upon Henry Evelyn's retirement from business, his two sons took over the Pierrepont Stores, which they operated until leased to the Empire Warehouse Company in 1888, shortly after the death of their father on March 28, 1888.
Henry Evelyn Pierrepont dedicated much of his time to the cultural development of the city, as well as its commercial expansion. He held a number of prominent positions, such as Trustee of Brooklyn Hospital, Trustee and President of Green-Wood Cemetery, Director of the Academy of Music, Director and President of the Brooklyn Club, and Director of The Long Island Historical Society.
Henry Evelyn Pierrepont II:
The eldest son of Henry Evelyn and Anna Maria Pierrepont, Henry Evelyn II was born in Brooklyn on December 9, 1845. Henry Evelyn, Jr. studied at Columbia College, receiving his B.A. in 1867. In 1869 he married Ellen A. Low, daughter of Ellen Almira Dow and Abiel Abbot Low, with whom he had six children. He and his brother, John Jay, soon took charge of the Pierrepont Stores, joining forces with Ferdinand N. Massa in the firm of Pierrepont Brothers. The brothers sold the Stores in 1888 and Henry Evelyn, Jr. retired from active business ventures, devoting his time to the further development of his real estate holdings. He continued his commitment to work within the community, most notably at Grace Church, of which his father had been a founding member and senior warden, a position which Henry Evelyn, Jr. also came to hold. Henry Evelyn Pierrepont II died in Brooklyn on November 4, 1911.
John Jay Pierrepont:
The younger of Henry Evelyn Pierrepont's two sons, John Jay was born in Brooklyn on September 3, 1849. John Jay married, on April 26, 1876, Elise de Rham, the daughter of Charles de Rham and Laura Schmidt, and the couple had one child who died before reaching one year of age. Elise Pierrepont died less than two years later on October 17, 1879 and John Jay Pierrepont lived out the rest of his life in the family house at One Pierrepont Place in Brooklyn, remaining an active member of Brooklyn society until his death on September 25, 1923.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The majority of the materials in this collection are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact cbhreference@bklynlibrary.org at least three weeks prior to research visit.
Related Materials
Center for Brooklyn History holds many maps once owned by the Pierreponts. Many of these were likely separated over time from this collection and relate particularly to Series 3 (Real Estate) and Series 6 (Waterfront and Ferries). Generally, these are maps of Hezekiah Beers Pierpont's property in Brooklyn Heights and of the land extending into the East River granted to the Pierreponts by New York State. The maps are especially strong at showing street lines, property development and waterfront along what is now the Pierrepont Street and Montague Street area of Brooklyn Heights across most of the nineteenth century. Several maps are mid-nineteenth century re-surveys or drawings of earlier surveys, thereby emphasizing changes over time. The Pierrepont maps are foldered together in CBH's Map Collection and can be requested as a complete set. Alternatively, specific maps can be requested by call number; individual maps can be identified through CBH's Map Portal.
CBH also holds some maps concerning Hezekiah's holdings in upstate New York counties. These are found in the New York State folder in the Map Collection. Finally, CBH's copy of Bernard Ratzer's Plan of the City of New York in North America: surveyed in the Years 1766 and 1767 was owned by Henry Evelyn Pierrepont.
CBH holds the John Jay Pierrepont photograph collection (call number ARC.197), which includes images in various formats of Brooklyn and waterfront scenes. These images can be viewed on the library's image database, PastPerfect.
The Robert Benson deeds at CBH (call number ARC.007) include several deeds from the late 1700s and early 1800s concerning Brooklyn Heights, including one between Benson and Hezekiah Pierrepont.
The Reformed Church on the Heights records (call number 1977.185) includes nineteenth century property records related to Love Lane and Pierrepont land.
The Luquer and Payne families papers (call number ARC.282) includes letters from Henry Evelyn Pierrepont to his wife (1865-1866); documents related principally to Seth Low Pierrepont concerning his disposition of the estate of Anna Jay Pierrepont, which included One Pierrepont Place; and documents concerning family burial lots at Green-Wood Cemetery.
The Brooklyn Certificate Collection (call number 1977.307) includes several membership certificates and other such recognitions awarded to Pierrepont family members.
CBH holds a number of materials on the library shelves related to the collection, including a copy of Hezekiah Beers Pierpont's will (call CS71.P53474.1854), Henry E. Pierrepont's Historical Sketch of the Fulton Ferry (call number F127.K5.P54.1879), and genealogies of the Pierrepont family. These materials can be found through Brooklyn Public Library's catalog.
Scope and Contents
The Pierrepont family papers illustrate the intersection of commercial, civic and personal interests across three generations of a Brooklyn family, principally in the nineteenth century. Although these papers span the period from 1761 to 1918, the bulk of the collection concerns the business dealings of Henry Evelyn Pierrepont from 1838 to his death in 1888. This especially includes an extensive set of records concerning the Pierrepont Stores, the family's warehouse on Brooklyn's East River waterfront. Included in the collection are correspondence, deeds, indentures, leases, accounting records, diaries, maps, invoices, receipts, business proposals, legal filings, clippings, and historical and genealogical manuscripts.
Included in the collection are a substantial number of deeds, leases, indentures, manuscript maps, title searches, and other documents concerning acquisition of land by the Pierreponts, primarily Hezekiah Beers Pierpont, in Brooklyn Heights and the adjoining waterfront. Similar documents concern the development of this land for personal use (e.g., the building of the family's home at One Pierrepont Place), civic improvement (e.g., the opening of streets, allocation of land to churches), and commercial ventures. Competing priorities among these interests can be seen in the collection, as in connection with attempts by cable car and elevated railway companies to build on or near Pierrepont property.
The Pierrepont's commercial activities are exceptionally well-represented in the collection. An extensive set of records for the Pierrepont Stores, from 1856-1888, includes day books, journals, ledgers, cash books, and records of deliveries received from arriving ships and goods transported to and from the Stores. In addition to the financial aspects of the business, the ledgers provide much information about the names of ships, their origin, and their cargo. Further, the Stores's time book is in the collection, with data on the names and daily hours of the workers. Correspondence, building construction and repair invoices, architectural plans, and business management documents concerning the Stores are in the collection. Henry's involvement as an officer of the Union Ferry Company, and the development of East River waterfront and ferry rights is well-represented in the collection with correspondence, proposals, maps, and legal documents. Account records related to Hezekiah's early nineteenth century distillery operation are in the collection.
A range of personal papers are in the collection. Many of these concern Henry and other Pierreponts engagement with civic institutions, such as the Long Island Historical Society, Brooklyn Academy of Music, Green-Wood Cemetery, and the Astronomical Society of Brooklyn. Henry's manuscript and supporting material for his published history of the Fulton Ferry is in the collection, along with other historical, biographical and genealogical materials. The collection includes a Civil War-themed scrapbook. Henry's rich diary from the last years (1877-1888) of his life is the collection. Correspondence between members of the Pierreponts, including Hezekiah's wife, Anna Maria, give insight into the Pierrepont's vision and concerns for the Montague Street area, for the Stores, and for their family welfare.
Account books; Bonded warehouses and goods -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Broadsides (notices); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Maps; Brooklyn Heights (New York, N.Y.); Business enterprises -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Cadastral maps; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Daybooks; Deeds; Diaries; East River (N.Y.); Ferries -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Imports -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Indentures; Invoices; Jefferson County (N.Y.); Journals (accounts); Landowners -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Ledgers (account books); Manuscripts (document genre); Manuscript maps; Oswego County (N.Y.); Real estate development -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Real property -- Ownership -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Scrapbooks; Shipping -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Waterfronts -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn Heights Railroad Company; Covered Tube Cable Railway Co. (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Long Island Historical Society; Nassau Cable Railway Company of Brooklyn (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Pierpont, Hez. B. (Hezekiah Beers); Pierrepont family; Pierrepont, Henry Evelyn; Pierrepont, Henry Evelyn; Pierrepont, John Jay; Pierrepont Stores (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Union Ferry Company (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Series 1: Mercantile, Farm and Distillery, 1802-1824; 1.1 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains materials relating to Hezekiah Beers Pierpont's business ventures and consists primarily of financial accounts of the distillery and of persons indebted to him.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged by subject matter.
  - Accounts of cow and cattle establishment and of persons indebted to H.B. Pierpont, 1818-1824 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Distillery Accounts, 1819-1824 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Agreement between Captain George Nichols, captain Jacob Smith and John Pierpont chartering the ship Active out of Salem, Massachusetts bound for Japan, 1802 (Box 91, Folder 1)
  - Account book of persons indebted to H.B. Pierpont, milkmen, and accounts of corn and rye received at the distillery from Long Island farmers, 1816-1822 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Series 2: Personal and Social Matters, 1823-1918; 1.5 Linear Feet
  This series primarily concerns the private, social, educational, and cultural pursuits of various Pierreponts, principally Henry Sr. Some important documents concern the Pierreponts's commercial and property interests; an example of this is an 1845 letter from Henry concerning Brooklyn Heights and Montague Street land transactions. Much of the correspondence in the series concerns the various civic committees and religious or cultural institutions supported by the Pierreponts, including the Long Island Historical Society, Astronomical Society of Brooklyn, Green-Wood Cemetery, Brooklyn Academy of Music, Committee on the University, and St. John's Church. Some correspondence and other documents concern the two Anna Maria Pierreponts (Constable and Jay); among these is an 1848 letter discussing the impact of a large fire in Brooklyn.
  Also found here are materials concerning Henry's elementary education and intellectual interests, family history and genealogy, and material concerning deaths and burial monuments. Among the historical notes is 1863 correspondence from Henry Sr. to Henry Stiles discussing the history of Brooklyn Heights. Some financial records are included in the series, such as the details of a 1845 wharf and land purchase and Henry's personal cash book (1825-1832). Also included is a 1907-08 series of National Photographic Library Postcards presented to the LIHS by Henry E. Pierrepont.
  The series is arranged by document form and subject matter in roughly chronological order.
  - Henry E. Pierrepont: early education (2 folders), 1823-1824 (Box 1, Folder 3, 4)
    General
    Includes the book Key to the exercises calculated to enable private learners to become their own instructors in grammar and composition. Includes the Yearly distribution of premiums for the pupils of the Lyceum.
  - Notebook of H.E. Pierrepont containing mathematical exercises, sketches, and essays, circa 1830 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Barometric record kept by H.E. Pierrepont, 1839-1840 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Article by H.E. Pierrepont on the tides of the Great Lakes, 1839 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - List of Subscribers to the Brooklyn Assembly, 1832, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Washington and Montague Park proposals published in local newspapers, also includes correspondence, 1845-1848, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Astronomical Society of Brooklyn: subscription book for the construction of an observatory, constitution, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    One piece of correspondence is in French.
  - Act concerning French Spoliation Claims, 1850, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Passport, H.E Pierrepont, Jr., 1863 (Box 91, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Henry and Henry Jr. (5 folders), 1832-1895 (Box 1, Folder 11-15)
    These folders include correspondence to and from the Henry Pierreponts. Most likely concern Henry Sr., though Henry Jr. is also represented. Correspondence to a Henry from one of the Anna Maria Pierreponts is included in a later folder.
  - Correspondence: John J., 1918 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence and other documents: Anna Marias (Constable and Jay), 1826-1902 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    This folder includes documents likely related to both Anna Maria (Constable) Pierrepont (Hezekiah's wife) and to Anna Maria (Jay) Pierrepont (Henry Sr's wife).
  - Correspondence: to Seth (Low Pierrepont?), 1909-1910 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - H.E. Pierrepont's personal cash book, 1825-1832 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Financial Documents, 1817, 1838, 1845, 1865-1870 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Includes financial details of a 1845 wharf and land purchase and a receipt for an 1817 survey.
  - Contents of H.E. Pierrepont, Jr.'s wallet, 1875-1902 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    The wallet itself was removed from this collection to BHS's museum collection. The contents include genealogical notes, correspondence, financial notes, and clippings.
  - Social cards, circa 1890 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Ellen Low Pierrepont: death and estate, 1872-1905 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Pierrepont Family History prepared by John Jay Pierrepont (photocopy), 1904, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Typescript recollections concerning Peter and Nancy (both blind from smallpox), children of Pierre Jay, circa 1880s (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Notes concerning history of plate once owned by Nathan Beers, circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - National Photographic Library Postcards and certificate presented to LIHS by Henry E. Pierrepont, 1907-1908 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Contains 1908 certificate of membership for Henry E. Pierrepont to the National Photographic Library, a placard declaring that it was presented by Pierrepont to the Long Island Historical Society, and several placards with photographs and descriptions on the back. The 1907 photographs are of natural phenomena in Alaska and the Southwestern United States such as Yellowstone Park, anthropological images of Southwestern Native peoples, and images of archeological sites. The images have detailed descriptions of what they depict on the backs of the individual placards.
  - Pierrepont House architectural drawings, undated (Box 93)
- Series 3: Brooklyn Real Estate, 1761-1873; 3 Linear Feet
  The series is only roughly organized, with the various legal documents followed by documents concerning One Pierrepont Place. The date range was determined by observation of the processing archivist and should be taken as circa dates.